The next stop is Broad Street.
Broad Street will be next.
Upstairs. This way.
He didn't come up this way?
Anything?
He's not up here.
Go back down.
Excuse me.
Go ahead and park
around the corner.
(CAR HONKS)
(SNIFFLING)
(TIRES SCREECH)
Visitors.
Do you mind
if I fetch my teeth?
Colonel, would you
turn around, please?
Sit down on the bed.
Let's go.
(CLEARS THROAT)
Uh, they're in the...
The teeth are in the... on the sink.
Look at me. We are agents
from the Federal Bureau
of Investigation.
Look at me!
I'm talking to you.
We've received information
concerning your
involvement in espionage.
You can either cooperate
with us right now,
or you'll be under arrest.
Do you understand, Colonel?
No, not really.
Why do you
keep calling me "Colonel"?
BLASCO: You need
to get dressed.
We have to search
your apartment.
Would you mind if I, uh,
cleaned my palette?
The paints,
it'll get ruined otherwise.
It's just behind you there.
I have a cloth myself.
Thank you.
All right, start searching the place.
All right,
search the mattress,
the bed, the floorboards,
his chair.
Would you put that
in the ashtray on the windowsill there?
BLASCO: Take a good look
at that desk.
FBI AGENT: Let's see the desk.
Wouldn't want
to get this ruined.
JAMES:
Don't say "my guy."
He's not "my guy."
BATES: Yes, he's "your guy."
Who are we talking about?
We're talking about a guy
who was insured by my client.
So, don't make him "my guy."
BATES: Okay, fine.
My point is, the guy
insured by your client,
he doesn't deny that
any of these things happened.
"These... These things"?
BATES: Yes,
these five things.
Wait, hold it,
hold it, hold it.
Not five things.
One thing.
BATES: Clearly,
it's five things.
Well, I'm sorry,
it's not clear to me.
Five things?
Explain it to me.
BATES: It's self-evident.
Okay, then tell me
what happened.
Tell me the story in a way
that makes sense for five things.
Fine, absolutely.
Your guy is...
Not my guy.
Insured by my client.
The guy insured
by your client
is driving down
State Highway 19
when he loses control
of his car and hits my five guys,
the five guys who hired me
to represent them
because you're not
honoring your claim.
You mean my client is not
honoring the claim, the insurance company?
(CHUCKLES) Mr. Donovan,
we're all clear on who's who, here.
Except my client
honors every claim.
They do, Mr. Bates.
Every single
legitimate claim,
up to the limit
of their liability,
which is $100,000
per accident,
in the case of
this man's policy.
And this is one claim.
According to your description,
"He hit my five guys."
The guy insured by my client
had one accident.
One, one, one.
Losing control of the car and
hitting five motorcyclists.
From their point of view,
five things happened.
Well, look, Bob.
May I? Bob?
"Jim."
If I go bowling and I throw
a strike, one thing happened.
Ten things didn't happen.
Jim, my guys
aren't bowling pins,
as much as your guy
may have treated them as such.
If... Let me finish.
Let me finish.
If your house
is insured for $100,000
and a tornado
carries it away,
it carried away one house.
It didn't pick up
every stick of furniture
and destroy it
in a separate incident.
If that is
what you're saying,
well, then there is never
any limit to our liability
and that is the end
of the insurance business.
And then, Bob,
nobody is safe.
Watters, Cowan and Donovan.
How may I direct your call?
Morning, Mr. Donovan.
Good morning, Alison.
I moved your 9:00 a.m.
with Prudential, sir.
Why did you do that?
I asked her to.
Is everything
all right, Tom?
Why don't you leave your stuff with Alison.
Come on inside.
Something pretty important
has come up.
Somebody's here to see us.
Natalie's getting
your coffee.
Nescafe, cream, two lumps,
right?
That's right. Thanks.
Lynn!
Jim!
Nice to see you again.
How's the family?
Great, good. Thanks.
How's Annie?
Homicidal. We had
the in-laws for the holiday.
Well, if she acts on it,
she'll have good representation.
(LAUGHS)
Now, what's up?
Okay, here's the thing.
The Soviet spy they caught,
we want you to defend him.
Here's the indictment.
Wow.
I'm not sure
I wanna pick that up.
The accused
doesn't know any lawyers.
The federal court
tossed it into our lap.
The Bar Committee took a vote.
You're the unanimous choice.
It was important to us...
It's important
to our country, Jim,
that this man is seen
as getting a fair shake.
American justice
will be on trial.
Well, of course,
when you put it that way,
it's an honor to be asked.
But, Lynn,
I'm an insurance lawyer.
I haven't done
criminal work in years.
It's like riding a bike,
isn't it?
You distinguished yourself
at Nuremberg.
I was on
the prosecution team.
Not the point.
You're no stranger
to criminal law.
Jim, look at the situation.
The man is publicly reviled.
And I will be, too.
Yes, in more
ignorant quarters.
But that's exactly why
this has to be done,
and capably done.
It can't look like
our justice system
tosses people
on the ash heap.
Suppose I did,
what's the evidence look like?
Pretty overwhelming.
Great. Great.
Everyone will hate me
but at least I'll lose.
(BOTH CHUCKLE)
Well, what do
you think, Tom?
The firm will suffer.
I have work here.
I think
it's a patriotic duty.
It's an important mission.
I told Lynn,
the firm can't say no,
and you'd have a tough time
saying no, too.
I think you have to defend
the son of a bitch.
So, you're doing it?
JAMES: Doing what?
Defending Abel,
the Soviet spy.
I may. I have to speak to...
Wait, how do you know?
Did they post it on the bulletin board?
No, I... I was
talking to Richard Earl...
Look, if I do this,
I'm going to need your help.
(CHUCKLES NERVOUSLY)
Can you work tonight?
Well, I have
a dinner date, sir.
It's Tuesday, right?
Yeah, no, I'm free, completely free.
Thank you, sir.
JAMES: But it's also an honor.
And the Bar Association
asked me
because they want
to show that even a spy
gets a capable advocate.
Well, maybe it's the kind of honor
we could do without.
Hey, honey,
what are you doing home?
I got stood up.
Well, that's despicable.
Who is this knot-head?
I'd rather not say.
MARY: Well, sit down.
We just started.
People are scared.
They're building
bomb shelters to protect themselves
from people like this man.
I go to the store,
people are buying
canned food and potassium tablets.
It's all about this man
and what he represents.
He's a threat to all of us.
A traitor.
ROGER: Who's a traitor?
The Rosenbergs were traitors.
Who were they?
They gave atomic secrets
to the Russians.
They were Americans.
They betrayed their country.
You can't accuse Abel
of being a traitor.
He's not an American.
(SOFTLY)
Oh, listen to yourself.
You're defending him already.
You're rehearsing it on me.
You said you were
just thinking about taking it.
I am just thinking about it,
just very hard.
Everyone deserves a defense.
Every person matters.
Jim, what do we deserve?
Do you know how
people will look at us?
The family of a man
trying to free a traitor?
He's not a traitor, Mary.
Yes, yes.
(PHONE RINGING)
Roger, get that! He's not a traitor...
Why do I have to do
all the work?
Oh! You wait till we say grace.
I'm hungry!
He's about the most unpopular
man in this country,
and you're trying
to take second place!
Yeah, and I'm third.
JAMES: Carol, you just dated the wrong guy.
I wanna eat.
Mary, don't make
this an argument
when we're not having
an argument.
You're against him,
I'm for him?
No, I'm not for him.
I'm not for the Russians spying on us.
I'm for his right to have a defense
in a court of law,
which is why they call it
a court of law.
I didn't mean
to interrupt dinner.
A court of law...
Hey, Doug.
Oh, no, not at all.
Hello, Doug. Jim was just flailing.
I'm not flailing.
Go ahead, Doug, you can join us for dinner.
We're having
meatloaf tonight.
So, you came over
to help Jim think about
whether he's
taking the case?
Oh, we're taking it!
It's exciting, isn't it?
(SIGHS)
Lord, we thank thee
for thy blessings
we are about to receive.
Thy bounty through Christ,
our Lord. Amen.
Good morning, sir.
My name is Jim Donovan.
These are my credentials.
I am a partner in
Watters, Cowan and Donovan.
I was admitted to
the New York Bar in 1941.
(DOOR BANGING)
(CHAIN RATTLING)
You have been charged
with three counts and 19 overt acts.
Conspiracy to transmit
United States defense
and atomic secrets
to the Soviet Union,
conspiracy to
gather secrets,
and failing to register
as a foreign agent.
Do many foreign
agents register?
If you don't mind
my asking, sir,
since your arrest,
where have you been?
I couldn't say for certain.
You don't know?
They drove me to an airport
and put me on a plane,
took me off the plane.
Somewhere hot.
It's hot here.
Hotter, very humid.
(SNIFFLING)
They put me in a room.
Were you beaten?
No.
I was talked to.
Offers were made.
What do you mean?
Offers of employment,
to work for your government.
I was told if I cooperated,
no further charges
would be made against me.
And I would be given money.
Hmm.
And you declined?
As you see.
Well, of course
I can't endorse that.
I feel duty-bound
to urge you
to cooperate with
the U.S. government.
Well, I said no.
Perhaps you could relay
to your friends at the CIA that I meant it.
No, no, no.
I... I don't work
for the agency.
I don't work
for the government.
I am here to offer my services
as your legal counsel.
If you accept them
as such,
I work for you.
If I accept you?
(SNIFFLES)
(SWALLOWS)
Are you good at what you do?
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm pretty good.
Have you represented
many accused spies?
(INHALES)
No, not yet.
This will be a first
for the both of us.
(LAUGHS)
Yes.
All right.
JAMES: "All right"?
You accept?
Yes, all right.
Good, okay.
Let's start here.
If you are firm
in your resolve
not to cooperate
with the U.S. government...
I am.
Yeah.
Then do not talk
to anybody else about your case,
inside of government or out.
Except to me,
to the extent that you trust me.
I have a mandate to serve you.
Nobody else does.
Quite frankly,
everybody else has an interest
in sending you
to the electric chair.
All right.
You don't seem alarmed.
(MUMBLES)
Would it help?
I... I would like
materials to draw with.
That's not possible.
A pencil, a piece of paper.
Cigarettes.
Please?
Mr. Donovan,
you have men like me
doing the same
for your country.
If they were caught,
I'm sure that you would
wish them to be treated well.
CIA AGENT: What's your name?
Francis Gary Powers.
CIA AGENT: Rank, service?
First Lieutenant,
United States Air Force.
Do you have any association
with the Soviet Union,
Lieutenant Powers?
Kidding?
Just answer the questions,
Lieutenant.
Yes, no,
or as simply as you can.
Do you have any association
with the Soviet Union?
Hell, no.
Do you know
why you're here?
POWERS: Mmm-mmm.
Is that a no?
Yes. I mean...
No, it's just "no."
Yes, I have absolutely
no idea why I'm here.
Eyes front, Lieutenant.
Yes, sir.
How'd you do in there, Gary?
Pretty good.
Think I got my name right.
(CHUCKLES) You probably
outscored Shinn, then.
(ALL CHUCKLING)
Who's winning?
Uh, that would be me.
Oh. Well, deal me in.
JOE: So, these are
all mine, then.
POWERS: I told you boys
not to play with him.
(DOOR CLOSES)
(CHUCKLES)
(BREATHES DEEPLY)
Okay, drivers,
here's the deal.
You've been selected
for a mission
which you are
not to discuss
with anyone
outside of this room.
No one.
I don't care who you trust.
Wife, mother, sweetheart.
The good Lord
when you pray at night.
You don't tell
any of them anything
of what
I'm about to tell you.
Each of you drivers has
met certain qualifications.
High level
security clearance.
Exceptional pilot ratings
in excess of
the required hours flight time
in a single-seat aircraft.
We are engaged in a war.
This war does not, for the moment,
involve men-at-arms.
It involves information.
You will be
collecting information.
You will be gathering
intelligence about the enemy.
The intelligence you gather
could give us the upper hand
in a full thermonuclear exchange
with the Soviet Union.
Or it could prevent one.
For public purposes,
as far as your wife or mother
or sweetheart
or the good Lord above,
your mission does not exist.
If it does not exist,
you do not exist.
You cannot be shot down.
You cannot be captured.
You work for the CIA now.
(DOOR CLOSES)
So, Jim, I heard your guy is
speaking with a phony accent.
Does he keep that up
all the time?
Actually, I'm pretty sure
that's just the way he talks.
He's got the Russian name
but a British passport.
Well, I doubt
that that's genuine.
So, Jim, where are we?
I see here...
Yes, uh, Judge, you see,
I just don't think that three weeks
is going to do it, here.
We... We got a massive amount
of evidence, as you know.
You wanna postpone?
Six weeks.
I mean, there's just myself
and my associate, basically.
Jim, is this serious?
Sir?
Is this serious?
Yes. Yes, indeed, it is.
You can see
in the filing...
Jim, this man is a Soviet spy.
Allegedly.
Come on, Counselor!
Your Honor.
Of course, I salute you.
We all salute you for
taking on a thankless task.
This man has to have
due process.
But let's not kid each other.
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
He'll receive
a capable defense.
And, God willing,
he'll be convicted.
Come on, Counselor.
Let's not play games
with this.
Not in my courtroom.
We have a date
and we're going to trial.
(DOOR CLOSES)
JAMES: Taxi!
Taxi!
I see your light on!
Son of a bitch.
Can't wait to get back
to Manhattan.
His light was on, right?
Son of a bitch.
MAN: Against their
level of comfort.
The statute hasn't changed.
Oh, excuse me, sir.
Pardon me. Sorry. Oh!
(CHATTERING CONTINUES
INDISTINCTLY)
Mr. Donovan.
What?
(TUTTING)
CIA.
Yeah.
I just wanted to chat.
How's the case going?
Case is going great.
Couldn't be better.
Mmm-hmm.
Has your guy talked?
Excuse me.
You met him. Has he talked?
Has he said anything yet?
We're not having
this conversation.
No, of course not.
No, I mean,
we really are not having it.
You're asking me to violate
attorney-client privilege.
Oh, come on, Counselor.
You know,
I wish people like you
would quit saying
"Oh, come on, Counselor."
I didn't like it the first
time it happened today.
A judge said it to me twice.
And the more I hear it,
the more I don't like it.
Okay, well, listen,
I understand attorney-client privilege.
I understand
all the legal gamesmanship.
And I understand
that's how you make a living.
But I'm talking to you
about something else.
The security
of your country.
And I'm sorry
if the way I put it offends you.
But we need to know
what Abel is telling you.
You understand me, Donovan?
We need to know.
Don't go "Boy Scout" on me.
We don't have
a rule book, here.
You're Agent Hoffman, yeah?
Yeah.
German extraction.
Yeah, so?
My name's Donovan. Irish.
Both sides,
mother and father.
I'm Irish, you're German.
But what makes us
both Americans?
Just one thing.
One, one, one.
The rule book.
We call it the Constitution
and we agree to the rules,
and that's what
makes us Americans.
It's all that
makes us Americans
so don't tell me
there's no rule book,
and don't nod at me like that,
you son of a bitch.
Do we need to
worry about you?
Not if I'm left alone
to do my job.
WILLIAMS:
From this moment forward
you will not refer to the U-2
as a spy plane
or reconnaissance aircraft.
You will refer to it
as "The Article."
The Article
has an 80-foot wingspan.
It's powered by a single Pratt and Whitney
J57 P-37 engine.
10,000 pounds of thrust
and a maximum speed
of 430 miles an hour.
She may not be quick,
but at your cruising altitude
of 70,000 feet,
nothing will
come close to you.
POWERS: 70,000?
The idea is the enemy doesn't
even know you're there.
It looks kind of flimsy.
Every extra pound of weight
costs a foot in altitude,
and we need
to accommodate the cameras.
That's a 4,500-millimeter
lens, times three.
A pin-sharp
panoramic camera
four times as powerful as any aerial
reconnaissance cameras we've ever used.
You're gonna be taking
pictures, lots of pictures.
At 70,000 feet,
The Article can photograph
2,000 square miles
of territory in one pass.
Now, drivers,
give Agent Sumner
your undivided attention.
The items you will need
on your mission are over here.
BLASCO: B camera,
Revere 8 model 40 magazine,
Keystone Capri K-25, silver.
Hollow-handle shaving brush.
Complete set of cipher tables
on edible silver foil.
Specialist photographic
equipment.
Yeah, we, uh...
We get the idea. Thank you.
Uh, excuse me,
Agent, uh, Bosco. "Blasco."
BLASCO: Sir.
There seems to be
a subsection to this list here.
Well, most of this stuff
came from his studio,
but the rest is from the
hotel room he was holed up in.
Where we found him.
The hotel room you searched?
Well, yeah.
Can I see the warrant?
The what?
Yeah, explain this to me.
There was a warrant.
A civil detention writ
for the arrest of an alien,
but there was
no search warrant
for suspicion
of criminal activity.
So, the search
and the evidence
that is
the fruit of that search,
that's all tainted
and should not be admitted.
What protections is he due,
Your Honor? The man is not...
The man is what?
He's Rudolf Ivanovich Abel.
He is a Soviet citizen.
He's not an American.
1886,
Yick Wo v. Hopkins.
The court held that even aliens,
in that case Chinese immigrants,
could not be held to answer for a crime
without due process of law,
including any alien that entered
the country illegally.
The Department of Justice
has its first allegiance
to the United States.
I don't see how an alien,
if he's here illegally,
how he suffered
deprivation of rights.
Rights as what?
An American?
Rights as what, Counselor?
We're in a battle
for civilization.
This Russian spy came here
to threaten our way of life.
Now, I have a courtroom
of people waiting.
Get out there,
sit beside the Russian.
Let's get this
over and done with.
And your motion is denied.
(SOFT MURMURING)
He should take some
insurance out on himself.
How did we do?
In there?
Uh...
Not too good.
Apparently, you're not
an American citizen.
That's true.
And according
to your boss,
you're not
a Soviet citizen either.
Well, the boss
isn't always right
but he's always the boss.
Do you never worry?
Would it help?
(DOOR OPENS)
(CLEARS THROAT)
All rise.
ALL: "I pledge allegiance
to the Flag"
"of the United States
of America,"
"and to the Republic
for which it stands,"
"one Nation under God,
indivisible,"
"with liberty and justice
for all."
MAN: (ON PROJECTOR) First,
you have to know what happens
when an atomic bomb explodes.
There is a bright flash,
brighter than the sun.
It can smash in buildings,
break windows all over town.
But if you duck and cover
like Bert,
you will be much safer.
There are
two kinds of attack,
with warning
and without any warning.
(WATER RUNNING)
JAMES: Mmm.
What's going on in here?
ROGER: Okay, Dad,
this is really important.
When the war begins,
the first thing they do
is cut off all the water
and all the electricity.
So the first thing we should do
is keep this filled,
use the shower in your room,
use the sink downstairs,
the garden hose outside...
Those are good ideas.
But, Roger, I don't see this
as being something
you ever have to worry about.
Yeah, but when
you hear the sirens,
there may not be enough time
to fill the tub and the sinks.
Not gonna be any sirens...
What is this?
When the bomb comes,
the Reds will aim
for the Empire State Building.
But the bomb goes off
at 10,000 feet up.
In Life magazine,
it's called an airburst,
and if the bomb
is 50 megatons,
the blast wave goes
out and out and out
and melts everything
from here to here.
Including where we live.
Here.
Yeah, right there.
But, you know, Roger,
no one is dropping
atomic bombs on us.
But the Russians want to.
You know that Russian guy
you're defending?
He's here
to get things ready
for the guys
who drop the bombs.
No, no, he's not...
Not here for that.
He's not even Russian.
He was born, we think,
in Northern England.
Yeah, but he's
a spy for Russia.
I don't even understand
what you're doing.
You're not a Communist,
so why are you defending one?
Well, because it's my job.
It never used to be.
CLERK: In the case of the
United States of America
versus Rudolf Abel,
as to the first count
in the indictment,
how do you
find the defendant?
Guilty or not guilty?
Guilty.
CLERK:
As to the second count?
Guilty.
CLERK:
As to the third count?
Guilty.
Your Honor, I make a motion
to set aside these guilty verdicts
against the weight
of evidence.
Denied.
The jury is discharged.
Thank you all.
I would like to add that,
if I were one of you,
I would've reached
the same verdict.
Sentencing will be November 15.
The death sentence is not
a foregone conclusion.
Don't worry.
I'm not afraid to die,
Mr. Donovan.
Although
it wouldn't be
my first choice.
You left this behind.
Oh, thank you.
Oh, thank you very much!
You've never asked me
if the charges were true.
If I am indeed a spy.
This is how we do it.
The case against you matters.
Making them prove it matters.
The fiction is...
Whether you did it or not
doesn't matter.
The state has to prove it,
that you're a spy.
So you're not curious?
No, not really.
I always assumed
you were an artist. (CHUCKLES)
My wife, she's the artist.
She's a musician
in the Children's Orchestra
of Moscow.
What instrument?
The harp.
Oh.
Then, she's an angel.
Standing there like that,
you remind me of a man
who used to come
to our house when I was young.
My father used to say,
"Watch this man."
So I did,
every time he came.
And never once
did he do
anything remarkable.
And I remind you of him?
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
This one time, I was
about the age of your son.
Our house was overrun
by partisan border guards.
Dozens of them.
My father was beaten,
my mother was beaten,
and this man,
my father's friend, he was beaten.
And I watched this man.
Every time they hit him
he stood back up again.
So they hit him harder.
Still,
he got back to his feet.
I think because of this
they stopped the beating.
They let him live.
(SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
(LAUGHING)
I remember them saying it.
(SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
It sort of means, like, uh,
"standing man."
Standing man.
(DOORBELL RINGS)
Hello, Jim!
Millie, you're a vision.
Mortie's busy
getting kitted out.
But come on in.
Scotch, Jim?
Oh, yes, please. Thank you.
Uh, just a drop of water.
Your Honor.
Hello, Jim!
Just going out.
Got a few minutes though.
March of Dimes thing.
Millie is active.
(CHUCKLES)
Well, thank you
for seeing me.
I just wanted to give you
my two cents on the sentencing.
And I thought maybe
I should pester you at home
as not all of my points
are narrowly legal.
Yeah, well,
it's that kind of case.
I hope I wasn't too scratchy
during the trial
but it's exactly
what you say.
Nothing about this
is narrowly legal.
There are bigger issues.
Bigger issues!
(CLEARS THROAT)
Thank you, thank you.
Uh...
Sir...
(CLEARS THROAT)
I think it could be
considered
in the best interests
of the United States
that Abel remain alive.
Why?
I'm not saying
I've made up my mind
but if he was
gonna cooperate,
work with the government,
he would've done it already.
- True, but the issue here...
- You can't...
Excuse me.
You can't say it's in the best interest
of the United States
that he spend
the rest of his days in a prison cell.
How is this
the national interest?
Not the incarceration
itself, sir.
It is possible that,
in the foreseeable future,
an American
of equivalent rank
might be captured
by Soviet Russia.
We might want to have
someone to trade.
Wow.
That sounds like
spinning what-ifs.
You could do that
till the cows come home.
It's my business, what-ifs.
I'm in insurance.
And there's nothing
implausible about this one.
It's entirely in the realm
of what could happen.
It's the kind of probability that
people buy insurance for.
If we send this guy to his death,
we leave ourselves wide open.
No policy
in our back pocket
for the day the storm comes.
Nice speech.
Sir, there is also
the humanitarian argument.
Should he die for doing the job
they sent him to do?
All right, Counselor.
I gotta run.
Good seeing you, Jim.
I'll walk you out.
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
BAILIFF: All rise.
The United States
District Court
for the Eastern District
of New York is now in session.
The honorable
Mortimer Byers presiding.
Be seated.
BYERS: The defendant
will please rise.
In the measured judgment
of this court
the following sentence,
based upon the jury's
verdict of guilty
as to each count
of the indictment,
is believed to meet the test
which has been stated.
Pursuant to the verdict
of guilty as to all counts,
the defendant is committed
to the custody
of the Attorney General
of the United States
for imprisonment
in a federal institution
to be selected by him
for a period of 30 years.
(GAVEL BANGS)
(CROWD MURMURING)
Marshals, you may take
the defendant into custody.
No... No electrocution?
No. No, no.
Why aren't we hanging him?
In the name of God,
why aren't we hanging him?
Sit down, sir!
MAN 1: He's a spy!
He's killing us with his lies!
In the name of God,
why aren't we hanging him?
That's right!
(CLAMORING)
MAN 2: He's a spy!
(CAMERAS FLASHING)
REPORTER 1:
Mr. Donovan! Mr. Donovan!
Just one question.
Just one question, sir.
(REPORTERS CLAMORING)
My hat! My hat! My hat!
Nobody here has a comment.
Mr. and Mrs. Donovan
are not answering questions.
REPORTER 2:
How do you feel now that
this national nightmare
is over?
REPORTER 3: Mr. Donovan, are
you happy with the verdict?
We're... We're in
firm ground on, uh, for a case on appeal.
REPORTER 4: Appeal?
Appeal, yes.
TOM: Jim, you did a great job.
You fulfilled your mandate
and then some.
But the man is a spy.
The verdict is correct
and there's no reason to appeal it.
There's ample
procedural reason.
We know the search
is tainted.
And Fourth Amendment issues
will always weigh more heavily
in an appellate forum.
We've got a good shot.
What the goddamn hell
are you talking about?
We were supposed to show
he had a capable defense, which we did.
Why are you citing
the goddamn Constitution at me?
Tom, if you
look me in the eye
and tell me
we don't have grounds
for an appeal,
I'll drop it right now.
I'm not saying that.
You know what I'm saying.
Tom is saying there's
a cost to these things.
That's right.
A cost to both
your family and your firm.
(SOFT ORCHESTRAL
MUSIC PLAYING)
I've missed music.
They checked the radio to make
sure there was no transmitter in it.
(CHUCKLES)
I'm sure they did.
Shostakovich. Mmm.
That's a very great artist,
Shostakovich.
Uh, I think
our strongest grounds
for reversal
are constitutional.
Our best chance is if the Supreme Court
agrees to review our case.
(MUSIC STOPS)
Jim...
You should be careful.
Careful.
♪ 77 Sunset Strip
TV ANNOUNCER:
Edward Byrnes.
♪ 77 Sunset Strip
TV ANNOUNCER:
And Richard Long.
DICK:
Good morning, Suzanne.
SUZANNE:
Good morning, Dick.
There is a special
delivery letter here for you.
DICK:
Oh, her.
(GUNSHOT)
(GASPS)
(GUNSHOTS)
(GASPING)
Mom!
What in God's name happened?
Honey, are you all right?
Mom!
Are you hurt?
MARY: I've got her.
Upstairs!
Are you all right?
I sat with my back against the wall, Dad!
Are you okay?
Are you all right?
Dad, I sat with
my back against the wall!
Good, good.
Away from the windows!
Good, good,
good, good, good.
Good boy,
good boy, good boy.
It's okay.
It's all right. (SOBBING)
It's all right,
they're gone, they're gone.
They're cowards.
They're gone.
We have detectives
canvassing the neighborhood.
Maybe we'll find
a description of the car
but I don't think
it's very likely.
We're gonna
need protection.
Oh, I have instructions
to leave two cars here.
It'll be pretty obvious
that this is a secure...
For how long?
I have to be in Washington
later on this week.
What are you doing?
What are you doing
to your family?
Pardon me, Officer?
You're still
defending this guy?
I mean, what are you
fighting for him for?
Okay, knock that off,
Officer.
I'll knock off nothing.
I was in the third wave
at Omaha Beach.
Hey, I did my time
in the service.
I was fighting these guys,
and you're defending them?
Why don't you just
do your job as an officer of the law?
Okay, I'm sorry.
Let's go outside. Come on.
You know what?
Just forget him.
What am I not getting here?
Outside, Officer. I'm sorry.
Defending a commie spy. Jeez!
(REPORTERS CLAMORING)
REPORTER: Do you feel
that you deserve this, sir?
(CLAMORING CONTINUES)
WILLIAMS:
Should it become necessary
to abandon the aircraft
over Soviet territory,
then there's a two-and-a-half pound
explosive charge
contained within
the fuselage.
Now, first,
you activate the circuits.
But to start
the 70-second timer,
you need to flip the switch
marked "Destruct."
It is imperative that these
flights remain a secret
and this equipment
does not fall into enemy hands.
What about us?
I don't know if you're kidding,
Lieutenant Powers.
I'm not.
What you know
about the plane
is as secret
as the plane itself.
If capture
is a foregone conclusion,
you go down with your plane.
Now, if you think
you can ditch and get away,
if you're close enough
to a border, fine.
You know
the ejection protocol.
But if you ditch,
you bring the dollar with you.
All right,
there's a pin inside.
You scratch your skin
anywhere, it's instantaneous.
If you think you are
about to be captured,
you use it.
Drivers, you understand me?
Spend the dollar.
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
JAMES: Mr. Chief Justice,
and may it please the court.
The "Cold War" is not
just a phrase, Your Honor.
It's not just
a figure of speech.
Truly,
a battle is being fought
between two competing views
of the world.
I contend
that Rudolf Ivanovich Abel,
"Colonel Abel,"
as he was called
even by the men
who arrested him,
is our foe in that battle.
Auxiliary power?
Connected and on.
Oxygen seat-pack supply?
Supply at 1,800 psi.
Inverter?
On, light out.
He was treated
as a combatant in that war
until it no longer
suited our government to so treat him.
Accordingly,
he was not given the protections
we give our own citizens.
He was subjected
to treatment that,
however appropriate
for a suspected enemy,
was not appropriate
to a suspected criminal.
Fuel transfer?
Transfer switch off.
Destructor?
Destructor safety.
Climb data card.
Installed in aircraft.
I know this man.
If the charge is true, he serves a
foreign power but he serves it faithfully.
If he is a soldier in the opposing army,
he is a good soldier.
He has not fled the field
of battle to save himself.
He has refused
to serve his captor.
to betray his cause.
He has refused
to take the coward's way out.
The coward
must abandon his dignity
before he abandons
the field of battle.
That,
Rudolf Abel will never do.
Shouldn't we,
by giving him
the full benefit
of the rights that define
our system of government,
show this man who we are?
Who we are.
Is that not the greatest weapon
we have in this Cold War?
Will we stand by our cause
less resolutely
than he stands by his?
(MISSILES WHIZZING)
(GASPING)
(SCREAMING)
(GRUNTING)
(BEEPING)
(SCREAMS)
(GASPING)
(PANTING)
RADIO ANNOUNCER:
The President announced
that a NASA weather plane disappeared
four days ago north of Turkey.
And the Space
Administration fears
that its pilot died
in the crash.
Radar showed the plane
wandering off course
deep into Soviet territory
before contact was lost,
complicating any effort
to recover it
or the remains of the pilot.
Now to news
out of Washington.
In a close vote today,
the Supreme Court
affirmed the conviction
of Russian spy
Rudolf Ivanovich Abel,
five votes to four.
The case presented
civil liberties issues,
according to the Russian's lawyer,
James B. Donovan.
When asked how he felt
about today's loss,
Mr. Donovan simply said,
"Tired."
I'll have more news for you
after this message.
WOMAN: (SINGING)
♪ Styling tricks
(WHISPERS) It's over.
♪ See the new,
exciting styling tricks
♪ You...
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
Marty.
I'll be damned if I can find the file
on that Prudential case.
I, uh, Mr. Watters had me
move it over to Jack Elwes's office
along with the first draft
of the appeal.
He did?
Yeah, he redrafted and filed that last week
while you were in Washington.
TOM: How long
have we been together?
You act as if
I've never closed a deal.
Set up a meeting.
Someplace fancy.
I'm betting Mr. Young
would like some of the finer things.
New York has to offer.
And I want you to give me
the summary of...
Do you know anyone
from Leipzig?
"Leipzig." Am I getting
hate mail from Germany now?
From East Germany.
(SNIFFLING)
Is it your wife?
No.
No, no, no, no.
She pretends to be
but it's not even a good pretense.
"I'm taking this liberty
to write to you"
"after having learned
from the newspapers"
"about your most
humane attitude"
"towards my
beloved husband, Rudolf Abel."
(CHUCKLES)
And do I write back?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
What's the next move
when you don't know what the game is?
TRANSLATOR:
Francis Gary Powers...
(SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
On the strength of Article Two
of the U.S.S.R. law
on criminal responsibility
for state crimes
to 10 years of confinement
with the first three years
to be served in prison.
The term of the punishment,
including
preliminary detention,
shall be counted
from May first,
nineteen hundred and sixty.
(CONTINUES SPEAKING
IN RUSSIAN)
(CAMERA SHUTTERS CLICKING)
ALLEN: Mr. Donovan,
thank you so much for coming.
It's a pleasure to meet you,
Mr. Dulles.
It's an honor, sir.
Nescafe, cream, two lumps.
Thank you.
Okay,
this letter you received.
Seems pretty clear that the Soviets
are making an overture here.
They're doing it
through East Germany
because they still don't want
to acknowledge Abel as a Soviet citizen,
much less a Soviet spy. So...
Lot of fiction going on.
Yes, sir, but to what end?
They got our guy,
our spy pilot.
We've got their guy.
Prisoner exchange,
I think that's what they're after.
Which could hardly be
a surprise to you, Counselor.
It's an eventuality
that I think you foresaw.
Yes, I sure did,
and I'm so rarely right. (CHUCKLES)
Well, congratulations.
Red letter day.
Now, we have our man
over there. Powers.
Good man, but with
a head full of classified information.
Abel has a head
full of classified information, too,
but he hasn't
given us a lick.
And, sir, take it from me,
he won't.
Yes, we know that,
but the Russians don't.
They want their man back
before he cracks.
And we want Powers back
for the same reasons.
JAMES: I think
you are saying, sir,
that there might be
a happy ending for everyone.
Yes, if we, um,
indulge their fiction.
We want you
to negotiate the swap
because you're
a private citizen,
so it's not
governments talking.
They don't acknowledge
Abel as a Soviet citizen,
and we don't acknowledge East Germany
as a sovereign country.
We haven't
recognized East Berlin
since it was annexed
by the Soviets in '45.
So I act as a negotiator,
representing...
You're not
representing anybody.
Not a government official.
You have no
official standing.
So, some fiction
on our side as well.
Correct.
Which means, of course,
you can't rely on any acknowledgment
or help if things go south.
CIA can't be responsible.
We can't be embarrassed.
Where do they want this
negotiation to take place?
There.
"There"?
East Berlin.
Well, isn't East Berlin
getting rather...
Oh, yes, the place
is getting complicated.
Yeah, complicated.
The Soviet side has been setting up
checkpoints for the past few months
to try to stop people
hemorrhaging to the Western sectors,
and it hasn't worked.
We have intelligence
to suggest
that they may go
one step further
and wall off
the entire Eastern sector.
Okay, that's it
in a nutshell.
The decision
is entirely yours.
You need time
to kick it around.
No.
No, I don't.
Well, fine. Fine.
Best that this all
remains confidential.
Let's not discuss any of this with, uh,
Mary or with anyone else.
Share the correspondence
only with us.
Let us know what they want to do
and when.
I've got no client,
no wife, no country.
Don't know what I'm doing
or when or who for.
You're doing it
for your country,
but your country
doesn't know that yet.
What about my client,
the other person in this equation? My guy?
Your guy?
You mean the Russian?
He's not your guy anymore,
Counselor.
Your guy is
Francis Gary Powers now.
What do I tell
Rudolf Abel?
Tell him not to drop dead.
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
(MAN SHOUTING IN
OTHER LANGUAGE)
(PANTING)
(CHILD CRYING)
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING
AND YELLING)
(BABY WAILING)
(CHILDREN CONVERSING
IN GERMAN)
(PANTING)
(MAN ON RADIO SPEAKING GERMAN)
Professor?
Papa went to university.
You shouldn't be here,
Frederic.
They're having
classes today?
He went to see.
That's where he goes.
What are you doing here?
I came to get you
and your father.
You have to come with me.
You might not get out tomorrow.
Just... Just leave?
Yes. Yes, yes, yes, leave.
Right now.
(CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
PRYOR: Go back. Go back.
I'll be okay, I'm American.
Go back.
Go back to your father's.
We'll find another way. Go.
(CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
Hey!
PRYOR: So, hi.
Papers, please.
Ich bin Student
Frederic Pryor.
Yes,
Student.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
(GRUNTS)
(GASPS)
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
My name's Frederic Pryor.
I'm an economics student.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
See? (GASPS)
It's my dissertation. My thesis.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
You see? Look, look.
Look "The foreign trade system
of the European Communist nations." Huh?
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
It was a lot of work.
(RAPID BREATHING)
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
No, that's my only copy.
(GRUNTS)
(SHOUTING IN GERMAN)
(DOG BARKING)
No! (CRYING)
MARY:
Tell me something.
It came up
at the last minute.
They have offices
in London.
These clients.
Not my idea.
Scotland, this
fishing expedition.
What kind of
fishing trip, Jim?
Salmon fishing.
Just tell me that you're
not gonna be in any danger,
that this is
just a routine business trip,
and I won't worry.
I need my passport.
Just give me something
to hold on to.
I don't even care
if it's the truth.
I'm doing this for us.
HOFFMAN: Mr. Michener, here,
is your Berlin escort.
He's an attache
with the U.S. embassy.
So, it's gotten goddamn complicated.
JAMES: Uh-huh.
As you know,
the last letter from Mrs. Abel,
whoever she is, talks about
a lawyer in East Berlin,
Mr. Vogel, whoever he is,
representing her interests, she says.
Yeah, Vogel says
he's gone to the Russian
embassy in East Berlin
and they may be ready
to trade Abel for Powers.
But no one knows who's who,
but essentially they're all Russian,
right?
Well, Soviet.
Well, we think so.
What do you mean?
Could we turn up the heat in here?
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
There's a wrinkle.
They might try
to throw you a curveball.
Try and get you to accept
another prisoner other than Powers.
Another American?
The, uh, East German Stasi
picked up an American student.
Frederic Pryor.
Uh, the kid they found on the wrong
side of the Wall.
He's a grad student
out of Yale.
Came over here to study economics.
JAMES: Mmm-hmm.
So, they're making noises
about trying this kid for espionage.
Grave offense, capital crime.
Well.
Vogel got in touch with us,
said he represents Pryor.
Wait a minute. Vogel represents Mrs. Abel
and this... This kid?
Yeah, he's busy.
Well, so,
what is he?
Vogel, is he, uh,
East German or is he Russian?
Well, try to figure it out
when you meet him.
At Russian embassy,
East Berlin, noon tomorrow.
Hoffman will show you
how to get there.
Wait, show me how to get there?
I'm gonna have an escort.
Right?
Well, that was the plan
but like I said, there's a wrinkle.
I won't be taking you.
Decision's been made.
No U.S. government personnel are to
cross the border until further notice.
How come?
It's too dangerous.
Yeah, the East Germans
grabbed this kid.
There's a degree of impunity
that we had not anticipated.
The point is that the East German agenda
and the Russian agenda
may not be
the same thing.
Try and figure it out
and act accordingly.
And try to make a deal.
Powers for Abel.
Well, what about this
college kid, Pryor?
Mmm-mmm.
Don't fall for that.
We can get him out
another time.
Powers is the whole
ball game.
Where's your room?
I'll be staying
at the Hilton.
It's not far.
This is a number here
in West Berlin.
Memorize it and
give it back to me.
No, no. I...
I mean, now.
The Soviets keep cutting
the international lines
but local calls
are okay.
Someone will pick up
day and night.
Now, this docket attached to your passport
will serve as your ticket
into and out of
the Eastern Soviet sector.
The meeting with Vogel
is set for noon tomorrow.
There are only a few routes
left to the East.
You take the S-Bahn, the station we showed
you on the way in.
You're gonna get off
at the Friedrichstrasse station here
and walk to the Soviet embassy
on Unter den Linden here.
Look at the map now.
You shouldn't take it with you.
You're looking at a map,
you're an American, you're a spy.
You could
well be detained.
Just avoid interacting
with people generally.
You don't...
You don't belong, so don't stick out.
Food is scarce over there
and things have started to fall apart.
There are gangs,
and rule of law is less firmly
established over there.
And definitely stay away
from the Wall.
On their side,
there's a line
cleared of buildings
along the Wall.
They call it
the "Death Line."
Cross it and
you'll be shot.
Is there any outcome here
where I'm not either detained or shot?
Don't worry too much
about what Michener said.
No, I'm worried about
what you're saying.
This kid, Pryor,
that the East Germans have,
how old is he?
Twenty-five. Why?
Same age as Dougie.
Who?
Eh, an associate of mine.
Frederic Pryor.
(CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
(JAMES SPEAKING GERMAN)
(BOTH SPEAKING GERMAN)
Okay, okay, okay.
(CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
(SNIFFLING)
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
JAMES: Danke.
(CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
So, we apologize
if this offends.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
Uh... (SNAPS FINGERS)
Coat?
(CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
(SNICKERING)
Okay.
(CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
(SHIVERING)
(COUGHING AND SNIFFLING)
Do you understand English?
Yes, sir.
I'm James Donovan.
I'm here to meet a Mr. Vogel.
Mr. Vogel.
He doesn't work here.
I'm just supposed to meet him.
That's all I know.
Mr. Donovan!
So we finally meet you.
(EXCLAIMING)
I'm Helen Abel.
How is our husband?
Oh. He's fine.
How is my Rudolf?
As good as
can be expected.
And we will
get him back, yes?
This is our daughter.
How do you do?
Lydia.
Are you Mr. Vogel?
(CHUCKLING)
No, no, no!
I'm not Vogel.
I'm cousin Drews.
This is Rudolf's
beloved cousin Drews.
Yes, cousin Drews.
I am cousin Drews.
Cousin Drews, yes.
I'm Helen Abel.
When will you see him?
When will your government
release him?
I'm a little,
uh, lost here.
I'm supposed to meet
a Mr. Vogel.
BOTH: Oh, Mr. Vogel
is our lawyer.
We were supposed to negotiate,
uh, the exchange.
To bring Rudolf here?
Yes, yes, to bring him here.
But it doesn't happen unilaterally,
do you understand?
It has to be
an exchange.
(SPEAKING IN OTHER LANGUAGE)
Not here?
(SOBBING)
(LYDIA SPEAKING
IN OTHER LANGUAGE)
LYDIA: Shh.
(LYDIA SPEAKING
IN OTHER LANGUAGE)
Shh. Shh.
(LYDIA SPEAKING
IN OTHER LANGUAGE)
(DREWS CONSOLING
Mr. Donovan?
Mr. Vogel.
No, no, no.
Goodness.
My name is Schischkin.
Ivan Schischkin.
I'm the second secretary
of the Soviet embassy.
(SIGHS)
It wouldn't be appropriate
for Mr. Vogel to join us.
He is a German national.
So you aren't here to...
To facilitate this meeting.
(SNIFFLES)
Uh, perhaps Mrs. Abel
would like to compose
herself privately?
And let Mr. Donovan
and myself to talk?
Thank you.
(DOOR CLOSES)
So, I'm confused.
Yes.
Uh, I don't care
who I talk to
if it's about
an exchange of personnel.
Are you the person
to talk to?
Yes, yes, yes, of course.
Uh, we should talk.
Please, have a seat,
Mr. Donovan.
(SNIFFLING AND COUGHING)
Uh, how did you arrive
to the Eastern sector?
The train.
The S-Bahn.
Ah, and you were alone?
Yeah.
And you are
credentialed?
Now, you must know
about me, sir.
I'm a private citizen.
I'm a lawyer in Brooklyn
in the United States,
and I've taken time
out of my busy schedule
to help my client,
Rudolf Abel.
I'm authorized to arrange
an exchange of Abel
for Francis Gary Powers.
This is a full
pardon of Abel
that will be signed
when the exchange actually takes place.
This is the only
reason I'm here.
I hope and expect to make
this arrangement quickly.
Abel for Francis
Gary Powers
and Frederic Pryor.
Mmm, we don't have Pryor.
No? You don't?
I've heard of Pryor,
but he's held
by the German
Democratic Republic,
not by the Union of Soviet
Socialist Republics.
Well, I'll tell you
the first problem.
The names of your countries
are too long. (CHUCKLES)
(CHUCKLES)
Yes, yes.
(SNIFFLES AND COUGHS)
If we release Powers,
it is only to
promote a goodwill
between our countries.
So, it cannot be
an exchange.
Perhaps...
Perhaps you could
release Abel
as a token of goodwill
to our friends in Germany,
and then,
some months later,
we would release Powers.
There is an idea.
No. That just won't work for us at all.
See, we need this to be
an exchange.
You can call it
what you want,
but an exchange
it must be.
We can have Abel here
within 48 hours.
We need Powers
at the same time we give you Abel.
Hmm. This is...
Can we call this
the "impatient plan"?
Well, you can call it
whatever you want.
(EXHALES)
I can relay your
impatient plan to Moscow,
see what they say...
(COUGHING)
But they will wonder
why so impatient.
Because I have a cold.
And I don't live in Berlin
and I want to go home.
They will think,
"Well, the Americans
must have gotten"
"all the information
that Abel had to give."
"And now they're impatient
to trade him,"
"hoping to get in return
this man, Powers,"
"that, perhaps,
has not yet given up"
"all the information
that he has to give."
This is not
an equitable trade, sir.
But what you're saying is,
if Powers has given up
everything he knows,
then Moscow would trade?
Why wouldn't they?
As for Abel, if he dies
in an American prison,
the next Russian operative
who gets caught
might think twice about
keeping his mouth shut.
And you never know.
Abel might want to see the sky again
and decide to trade Russian
secrets for small American favors.
How can we know this?
We little men,
we just do our jobs.
Like Lieutenant Powers.
He's just a pilot.
He was making photographs
from 70,000 feet
when he was shot
from the sky.
People in my country
consider this
an act of war.
We have to get off this
merry-go-round, sir.
The next mistake
our countries make
could be the last one.
We need to have
the conversation
our governments can't.
I will ask Moscow.
Who knows
what they will say.
There are a lot of people,
Mr. Donovan,
who doesn't want this
exchange to ever take place.
Can you come back tomorrow
to discuss their answer?
Powers for Abel.
And Frederic Pryor.
As I said,
Pryor is in the hands
of the organs of.
State Security of the German
Democratic Republic.
I'm confident you can
make arrangements.
I am merely a secretary
in the embassy
of foreign power.
Okay, okay.
You have to see Mr. Vogel.
I'll give you his address.
There actually is
a Mr. Vogel?
Why would you
imagine otherwise?
Uh, it's a short cab ride.
And please, Mr. Donovan,
wear an overcoat
in this weather.
I had mine
stolen from me.
What do you expect?
It was from
Saks Fifth Avenue.
Wasn't it?
(MAN ON RADIO
SPEAKING GERMAN)
VOGEL: Mr. Donovan.
(CLEARS THROAT)
Mr. Vogel.
VOGEL: Please come in.
Danke.
Sorry about the embassy.
But the Soviets decided
not to host me.
Very irritating.
I am still trying
to grasp each party's...
Status?
Yes. And interest
in the proceedings.
Oh.
It's a new world.
All very disorienting,
isn't it?
Let me tell you
what I have to offer.
(TURNS OFF RADIO)
I'm a good friend...
"Friend."
No, he's older.
"Protege"?
Of the attorney general
of the German Democratic Republic.
Sit down, please.
This unfortunate,
Frederic Pryor,
he was in the wrong place
at the wrong time.
But every accident,
properly viewed,
is an opportunity,
isn't it, Mr. Donovan?
Well...
Your country refuses to recognize
the German
Democratic Republic.
They prefer to
make up stories
that the GDR doesn't
exist, for instance.
Sorry.
As a means of forcing your
government's recognition
of this real place, sir,
in which you
find yourself,
the GDR,
the attorney general is
happy to negotiate with you
as a representative
of your government
for Mr. Pryor's return.
Mr. Vogel,
I'm not here
as a representative
of my government.
All right.
(CHUCKLES)
I think that's childish,
Mr. Donovan.
Well, I... I have
no official status.
Fine.
You do not represent the USA,
I do not represent the GDR.
My client is Lydia Abel,
Rudolf's wife.
And I have also...
Lydia is the daughter.
Helen is the wife.
Well...
I am prepared to offer
Frederic Pryor's exchange
for Rudolf Abel's.
(PUTS GLASS DOWN)
Then let's be clear.
We will produce
Rudolf Abel.
You will produce,
at the same time, the student, Pryor.
At the same time?
Absolutely.
The exchange on offer
is a Russian at the end of his life
for an American student
at the start of his.
Schischkin? He's not
an embassy secretary.
Ivan Schischkin is the KGB's
chief in western Europe.
(CLEARS THROAT)
Well, whatever he is,
he's relaying our
proposal to Moscow
and they'll decide.
Could I borrow a coat?
I lost mine.
How did you
lose your coat?
You know, spy stuff.
I'll get you another coat.
Good, because... (EXHALING)
So who is, uh...
Who is this Vogel?
Him, we don't know.
He might be what you
said he said he is.
Friend of
the attorney general.
Just some guy the GDR
tapped to handle this.
Sounds like
the East Germans
are fighting for
a place at our table.
The GDR gets Abel back
for the Russians,
winning their respect...
(COUGHING)
And capturing the headlines
for their cause.
Which, of course,
puts East Germany on the map.
But we don't care
about their map.
Stick with
the Russians.
Stick with the Russians.
It's Powers for Abel.
So, does all this mean
this might actually happen?
Yeah, that's what
you seem to be telling me.
We'll put Abel on a plane,
he'll be here Friday.
So, if Schischkin
gets the okay,
all that's left is the
mechanics of the trade.
How we swap our guy
for their guy.
Our "guys." Two guys.
Powers and Pryor.
No, now don't go
bleeding heart on me.
Powers is the whole
ball game.
Forget this
Ivy League boy,
who obviously thought
it was a good idea
to study Soviet
economics in Berlin
in the middle
of the Cold War.
Powers is who we need.
You don't even
like Powers.
Everybody hates Powers.
He didn't kill himself and he let the
commies parade him on television.
He's the most
hated man in America.
After Rudolf Abel,
maybe.
And me.
Now wake up!
(BOTH SHOUTING
IN OTHER LANGUAGE)
POWERS: I gotta sleep.
I just gotta sleep.
(GRUNTS)
I told you,
you can sleep
once we talk
what we need to talk.
You must focus on me.
Your government doesn't care about you.
You know that.
Any of you.
You know that twelve
U-2 pilots incurred brain damage?
They're vegetables because of altitude,
insufficient oxygen.
But they keep you
flying, Gary.
You and your friends.
They gave you this.
A scratcher, yes?
Potassium cyanide.
Does that look like
they care about you?
(POWERS GROANING)
(POWERS GASPING)
What is the construction
of the destructor unit?
By what means
is this unit operated?
With what explosives
is the unit charged,
and what destruction
is it capable of?
I don't know.
The pilots were never shown
any of the equipment.
How wide far
can the radar
map an area during
an overflight?
I don't know,
I don't know!
Were you making
the overflight on April 9th
over the industrial area
and MiG bomber base
at Baranovichi?
I was not.
This was my
first overflight.
I need to know about
engine-out to glide ratio.
How the plane
gets so high.
We know it reaches
altitude of 70,000 feet.
Gary, we know this.
And I need to know
where the planes have flown.
Where they
have flown, Gary.
And we must have
this talk now.
Now.
And then you can
sleep a little.
CIA AGENT:
Sir, wake up.
Wake up, sir.
Sir, can you come with me, please?
Yeah.
We gotta move.
Yeah, of course.
Can you come with me, please?
Yeah.
Okay.
Got your glasses?
Uh-huh.
What time is it?
It's late, but we need to talk,
and then we need to
get on a plane, okay?
Yeah.
Yep. Upsy-daisy!
Upsy-daisy.
That's right.
There we go.
Keep it moving.
Thank you.
Other way, other way.
(CLEARS THROAT)
There we go.
You say a plane?
This way, please.
Keep moving.
IVAN: So, I received
a favorable decision
from Moscow
on your proposal
that we help our friends in the German
Democratic Republic
by exchanging
Mr. Powers
for Mr. Abel.
That's swell.
May I suggest the Glienicke Bridge
as a place of a swap?
Why not Checkpoint
Charlie?
(GRUNTS) We're not
looking for publicity.
The Glienicke Bridge
is very quiet,
especially early
in the morning.
Glienicke Bridge.
I'll run that by our side.
We can have Abel here
on Friday.
So, Saturday morning?
(CHUCKLES)
Always impatience, yeah?
I want to get home
and get into bed.
So, Saturday morning?
5:30?
All right.
We're done here.
This is a number,
in case anything
should come up.
All right.
Someone will answer
at any hour.
I don't expect
to use it.
Shall we toast
the arrangement?
Why not?
Armenian brandy.
Good bracer for your cold.
Thank you.
Would you mind...
This is not part
of our business
but I'd like to ask you
a couple of questions.
You do not
have to answer.
I shall answer
what I know.
I like this guy,
your guy.
What happens to your guy
when he gets home?
Well, we have to make
a determination
whether our guy
is now your guy.
Now, as I said
to you before,
he's acted
honorably.
He's still your guy,
believe me.
Of course you will
say that if it were true
and if it were
not true.
I guess it has
come down to that, huh?
Well, forgive me
for pushing,
but is he
in any danger
if the determination
is made?
Well, goodness.
As things are now,
everyone is in danger.
Cheers.
Na zdorovie.
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
(SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
There will be no exchange
on Glienicke Bridge.
Excuse me, sir.
There will be
no exchange.
Not for Frederic Pryor.
Mr. Vogel, I thought
yesterday we had agreed.
We agreed on an exchange,
Abel for Pryor.
Now I learn you are
a rug merchant
selling the same rug
to two customers.
Abel for Pryor you sell to us.
Yeah.
And Abel for Powers
you sell to the Soviets.
I'm not quite sure
what the problem is
if the arrangement satisfies
two parties or three or four.
What difference
does it make?
The arrangement does not
satisfy this party.
(CLEARS THROAT)
Now, Mr. Vogel, please...
Obviously you do not know
who you are dealing with.
Here's the interest
of the German Democratic Republic.
To deal with,
and to be seen to be dealing
with another sovereign power,
the United States.
An equal power.
Instead you treat us
as stooges
for the Union of Soviet
Socialist Republics.
Can we just call them the Russians?
It'll save time.
I have an appointment, sir.
I think it's you
who are wasting time.
JAMES: Now, tell me if
I am describing this wrong.
You have a kid,
a university student,
someone you know
is not a spy,
who's no threat to you.
And in exchange
for this person
who is worthless to you,
you play an equal part
in an exchange
between the Russians
and the Americans.
And this is one transaction
between us and the two of you.
We're not trying to do
two things here, sir.
We're just doing one thing.
One, one, one.
It's hard for me to see how the Republic of
East German Democrats is being slighted.
You agreed with the Soviets
without consulting me.
Is this a negotiation
or a conspiracy?
For it to be
a conspiracy,
there would have to be
harm to you, sir.
There's just benefits here.
We're of agreeing interests.
No, you decide
they agree.
Where is your
appointment, sir?
In the West.
Ku'damm.
Good.
VOGEL: Look around you.
How does the Eastern sector
compare with the West? Hmm?
(CHUCKLES)
Our Russian friends
have decided that
we should not rebuild
our capital city.
But we live in this ruin
made by our Russian friends.
Go ahead, make your deal
with these Russians.
We won't be part of it.
There is no deal
without Pryor.
We are not
leaving him here.
Is this your position
or your government's?
Sir, I'm here.
I'm talking to you.
But you are not a representative
of your government.
You don't know who you are.
Neither do we.
You should be careful.
This is not Brooklyn, Mr. Donovan.
(HORN HONKS)
Look, sir.
You must know that
in every respect that matters,
I represent
my government.
You know who I am.
Do I?
(SIREN WAILING)
(SIGHS) Uh-oh.
Do you have
the proper papers?
Of course not.
It doesn't matter.
An American lawyer
like you
can talk your way
out of anything.
Can't you?
(CONVERSING IN GERMAN)
You go with him.
Why?
It's passport problem.
What... What problem?
What's the problem?
You go with him.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
And remember,
we control the fate
of Frederic Pryor.
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
(SNIFFLES)
(GUNFIRE)
(ALL GRUNTING)
(ALL GASPING)
JAMES: My God!
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
(CLEARS THROAT) Yeah,
I'll start with some coffee, please.
Then I'll have
the Hilton combo
and the American
breakfast.
And coffee.
Both breakfasts?
Yeah, yeah.
One first or...
Both first, both.
Whenever they're ready.
And coffee.
Hmm.
You shouldn't be here.
Well, sometimes
in Germany,
you just want a big
American breakfast.
What happened?
Where were you last night?
Vogel arranged for me
to spend some time in the East.
Oh, Jesus.
Frankly, it's not
that much worse
than where you have me
here in the West.
So the Russians are fine
with the exchange,
but now Vogel is saying
that the East Germans won't do it.
We're not gonna
get Pryor.
Great, good.
So the Soviets are set.
We get Powers.
Well done.
JAMES: No, the East Germans
won't do it.
We won't get Pryor,
and that kid matters.
Every person matters.
Sure, that's why you tried.
That's why you tried.
Abel's on his way,
so we're all set for tomorrow morning.
Wait a minute.
Makes things simple. Makes things simple.
We are not
getting the kid.
Yeah, I understand.
We're set.
We can ignore the message
we got this morning.
What message?
From the East Germans.
They called the number
I gave you.
They said they wanted
to speak to you today.
Vogel called?
No, um...
Office of, uh,
Harald Ott,
East German
attorney general.
Wanting what?
What does he want?
Well, to talk to you.
But it's okay,
I can't ask you to go back there.
And listen, you seem to be
persona non grata to some elements,
so we won't
push our luck.
So he wants to see me.
What time?
Oh, no, no. Now, listen.
(STUTTERING)
You don't need to go.
In fact, you shouldn't go.
In fact, you can't go.
We're set with the Soviets.
We don't want to screw it up.
I'm not gonna screw it up.
You're not going!
Don't be a pain in the ass.
Oh, I ordered.
Enjoy your big
American breakfast.
(SIGHS)
I thought it should
be negotiated
at the highest level
as a courtesy to you.
I thank you, sir.
I don't know how things
became so confused.
Well, I guess sometimes
they just do.
For sake of clarity,
I say we are fully
prepared to exchange
the so-called student, Pryor,
for Rudolf Abel.
I understand from Mr. Vogel
that Pryor is very important to you.
JAMES: Yes, but...
Ah, we'll do a memorandum
to that effect.
Oh, a memorandum.
Certainly, we commit
to a bi-lateral exchange.
Yes, yes, sure. I'm not sure
what that means but...
My country also insists
on Francis Gary Powers.
No!
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
This is how things
became so confused.
Powers. What use
is he, sir?
You want him back for
punitive reasons?
What's done is done.
He has divulged
what he will divulge,
as no doubt
Abel has also.
We are offering instead
someone who you insist is innocent.
And this is right.
This is who
you should retrieve.
The future.
Look to the future.
(PHONE RINGING)
Ott.
(RINGING CONTINUES)
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
I'm sorry. If you could
give me a moment, sir.
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING)
(BELLS RINGING)
I'm very sorry, sir.
The attorney general regrets
that he had to leave
on urgent business.
He left?
Yes. Many apologies.
I've been waiting
for over an hour.
Very sorry, sir.
Young man.
Come here.
It's all right.
Uh...
Take a seat.
Oh, come on, come on.
Sit down.
Do you like
your job here?
It's a very
good job, sir.
It must be.
Must be interesting.
Oh, yes, sir.
And important, too.
And your English is...
Is good.
Yes, I hesitate to say
it's excellent.
But it's excellent,
sir.
Good, good.
Good.
See, I just lost my
negotiating partner,
and I need
somebody to talk to,
and you seem like
a reasonable young man.
Can I talk to you?
Uh...
It's all right.
(CHUCKLES)
It's all right. I just...
I just need you to give
a message to your boss.
But it has to be
very, very, very clear.
You understand?
Yes, sir. But perhaps
you should wait until he...
No, no. The thing is,
I have this cold and I wanna get home
and get in bed.
(BLOWS NOSE
AND CLEARS THROAT)
Can you give him
the message?
Certainly.
Well, this is
the message.
"There is no deal for
Abel unless we get Powers and Pryor."
Do you understand?
Yes, sir.
It's arranged for
tomorrow morning.
It will not happen
unless we get two men.
Those two men.
Two, two, two.
Yes, sir.
If there is no deal,
your boss must tell
the Soviets.
He has to tell
the Soviets
that they are not
getting Rudolf Abel.
Yes, sir.
Oh, and tell him this.
That so far, Abel has been
a good soldier,
but he thinks
he's going home.
(COUGHS)
If we had to tell him
that he's not going home,
that the Soviets
don't even want him,
that he's never
going home...
Well, I imagine his
behavior might change.
And who will be held
responsible for that?
(CHUCKLES)
That's a long message.
Uh, did you get it all?
Yes, sir. Got it.
Good.
You're a good man.
Oh...
And also tell him
there's no deal
unless we hear
before the end of
business today.
He has the number.
If the exchange
isn't gonna happen,
no reason for everybody
to get up first thing in the morning.
(CHUCKLES) No, sir,
that would be pointless.
You're kidding me!
Not really.
I need some change.
This is exactly
what you weren't supposed to do.
My instructions were
to feel out the situation.
Your instructions
were to get Powers, not Pryor.
That was not the original deal.
You fouled it all up!
How do you know?
I feel pretty good about it.
You fucked it all up!
Oh, don't worry.
I think it's
gonna be fine.
How do you know?
You don't know that.
(SPEAKING GERMAN)
United States.
New York, New York.
Danke.
Look, this whole thing
has been to feel me out.
Would I swap one for one
and which one?
But I said
"No, two for one."
So they know
where we stand.
Yeah, what if they think
about it and say, uh...
"Forget it! You keep our guy,
we keep your guys"?
Well, then I have
fucked it all up.
Hey, honey! It's me.
Yeah. The fishing's
been great.
I'm in London,
just for one more meeting,
then I'm on my way home.
Yeah, yeah, I remember
that marmalade.
It's that shop
right by Regent's Park.
All right, I will
if I have the time.
Hey, can I say
hi to Roger?
Could I say hi
to the girls?
Is anyone not busy?
Have they even noticed
I'm not around?
(SNIFFLING)
(PHONE RINGING)
We're on.
Two for one.
Hot dog.
(ALL LAUGH)
Let's have a drink.
One wrinkle.
What is that?
They won't release
Pryor with Powers, not at the bridge.
They'll release him
at the same time.
When the Russians give us
Powers on the bridge,
they'll release Pryor
over Checkpoint Charlie.
What does that mean?
I think it means,
"We wanna have the last word."
But they will do it.
You tell me.
You felt them out.
Where are they?
Where's our guy?
They're late.
Nobody's late.
We're early.
May I?
Yeah.
(SNIFFLING)
JAMES: Hoffman.
HOFFMAN: Yeah?
JAMES: I think they have...
HOFFMAN: What?
Snipers.
HOFFMAN: Well,
I'm sure they do.
How are you
sure they do?
Because we have snipers.
Step out, sir.
Jim.
Dear Jim.
(CHUCKLES)
How are you?
Happy to see you.
Have you arranged
all this for me?
Well, let's see what this is before I...
I take credit for it.
Any word about Pryor
from Checkpoint Charlie?
(DOG BARKING)
(INDISTINCT CHATTERING
IN GERMAN)
Nothing cooking yet.
Excuse me, sir.
This is Lieutenant Joe Murphy,
United States Air Force,
here to identify Powers.
Lieutenant Murphy.
Sir.
There may be
a slight glitch.
I was a young man
when I left.
Who will they find
to identify me?
Well, I hope it's not your
East German family.
I doubt they could
identify each other.
(WHISTLING)
Looks like our party.
Well, let's go.
You can stay here,
Donovan.
Not likely.
Open the gate.
What do you think will happen
when you get home?
Uh, I think...
I'll have a vodka.
(CHUCKLES)
Yeah.
But, Rudolf, is there
not the possibility...
That my people
are going to shoot me?
Yes.
You're not worried?
Would it help?
To answer your question,
my friend, I acted honorably.
I think they know that.
But sometimes
people think wrong.
People are people.
Let's see how they
greet me.
What can I look for?
If I'm embraced or just
shown the back seat.
(SPEAKING IN OTHER LANGUAGE)
ABEL:
Da.
(CONVERSING IN RUSSIAN)
Take off the hat.
Hey, Powers.
Hey, Murph.
Yeah, that's Powers.
SCHISCHKIN: All right,
Mr. Donovan. We go now!
Hang on.
Believe me,
I will tell you.
There's no one here.
They're releasing another man
at Checkpoint Charlie.
We're just confirming
that he's there.
SCHISCHKIN: Now!
As per plan,
if you please.
(SNIFFLING) Let's go.
Pryor will show up
or he won't. Let's go.
They're waiting to see
if we'll do it without him.
We just have to stand here,
show them we won't.
I don't give a shit
what they want.
We have our objective.
Go ahead, Abel.
Go ahead, sir.
You can go.
If it is not to plan,
we go home.
We exchange now
or we go home!
You're waiting for another man?
Yup.
You want him, too.
I want him.
Doesn't matter
what he wants, sir.
I'm in charge and
you are free to go.
Please go.
Walk across.
(SPEAKING RUSSIAN)
(CHUCKLES SOFTLY)
I can wait.
It's something.
I'm not sure yet.
Hang on!
(WHISPERS) Let's go.
We got him!
Uh, I, uh...
I sent you a gift, Jim.
It's a...
It's a painting.
I hope it has some
meaning to you.
I'm sorry. I didn't think
to get you a gift.
This is your gift.
(SNIFFLING)
You okay?
Let's go, let's go,
let's go!
Mr. Donovan.
Colonel Abel asked me
to give this to you.
Pardon me, sir.
Were you in charge
of this thing, sir?
Yeah.
Well, I gotta thank you.
I gotta thank somebody.
I gave them nothing.
It doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter
what people think.
You know
what you did.
(BOTH EXCLAIMING)
Welcome home.
(SIGHS IN RELIEF)
What a trip.
(KISSES)
MARY: Mmm.
JAMES: Mmm.
You okay?
Yeah, I'm fine.
Did you get the marmalade?
Yes, yes.
Yep. Yep.
I did.
As ordered.
(CHUCKLES)
(GASPS) Jim.
This is from Arno's.
So?
On the corner!
Well, honey, I was busy.
I'm sorry. We were so busy.
Oh, for Pete's sake.
How's Roger? Is he home?
He's home.
Carol's home, Peggy's home.
Everyone's home.
CAROL: Mom!
Come quick! Look!
Mom, come here!
PEGGY: Mom, come here!
ROGER: Come see this! Look! Watch!
PEGGY: Come on!
Francis Gary Powers
has been released from prison
in the Soviet Union
and turned over to
American authorities
early this morning
in Berlin.
The President has commuted
the sentence of Rudolf Abel.
Mr. Abel has been
deported
and has been released
in Berlin.
Efforts to obtain
Mr. Powers' release
had been underway
for some time.
In recent efforts,
the United States
government has had
the cooperation and assistance
of Mr. James B. Donovan,
a New York attorney.
Frederic L. Pryor,
an American student
held by East German
authorities
since August of 1961...
I thought Daddy
was fishing.
For salmon.
Abel now has disappeared
into the communist world.
Powers is here,
answering questions.
And Donovan has gone back
to his law practice.
And now, here is
George Fenneman,
speaking for the Douglas Fir
Plywood Association.
Following his return to Russia,
Rudolf Abel was reunited with his wife and daughter.
He was never publicly acknowledged by the Soviet Union as a Spy.
Gary Powers died in a helicopter crash in 1977,
while working for KNBC news.
He was posthumously awarded the CIA Director's Medal,
and the USAF POW Medal in 2000 and the Silver Star in 2012.
In 1962, Frederic L. Pryor received his Ph.D. in Economics from Yale University.
He is currently Professor Emeritus of Economics,
and Senior Research Scholar at Swarthmore College.
Following the successful conclusion of the Powers-Abel exchange,
James Donovan was asked by President Kennedy to undertake
further negotiations on behalf of the U.S.
In the summer of 1962,
he was sent to Cuba to discuss with Fidel Castro
the terms of the release of 1,113 prisoners
held after the Bay of Pigs invasion.
When Donovan finished negotiations,
he had secured the release of 9,703 men, women and children.